Today's דף Daf is דף סמך Daf Samech and we pick up
with the let's read from the תני עלה. Tani Ala. Now this
is a case where we're four lines down from the top. So
this is a case that we've seen before about a person who's
a ספק Safek נזיר טמא Nazir Tamei meaning maybe he touched a
dead body and a ספק מצורע. Safek Metzora. And basically he has
to wait 120 days: 60 days to get out of מצורע Metzora
and 60 days to get out of his נזיר טומאה. Nazir Tuma.
And the basic explanation is that because there are going to be
four shavings. As a נזיר מצורע Nazir Metzora you shave when you
start, when it clears up. As a מצורע Metzora you'd shave when
it clears up and then you'd shave seven days later at the
end of the טהרה Tahara process. And a נזיר טמא Nazir Tamei
you'd shave when you became טמא Tamei and then and then you
would shave at the end of the נזירות. Nezirus. So there would
be four shavings, but normally that could happen pretty quickly. But because
he might be a נזיר טהור Nazir Tahor in any of these
statuses, he has to wait 30 days between each
shaving because because he might be a נזיר טהור Nazir Tahor and
then he can't shave in the middle of his נזירות. Nezirus. So
we don't have it up on the board anymore, so maybe I'll
use this here, maybe we'll use an opportunity
to do that again quickly.
Okay, why not. So here's basically the story. What does
a normal נזיר Nazir do? A normal נזיר Nazir goes 30 days
and shaves גילוח Giluach
and קרבן.
Korban. Okay? A נזיר טמא Nazir Tamei meaning טומאת מת, Tumat Meit,
okay, goes seven days and then does גילוח Giluach and קרבן Korban
and then does 30 days of טהרה Tahara and then another גילוח
Giluach and קרבן.
Korban. Technically that's day 37.
Okay,
a
מצורע Metzora does
even
if you're a נזיר מצורע Nazir Metzora because the shaving or whatever
for but if you're definitely a מצורע, Metzora, okay, then it would,
your shaving would go, you would shave even though you're a נזיר,
Nazir, a נזיר טהור Nazir Tahor whatever, that's the הלכה, Halacha, that
the shaving of a definite מצורע Metzora overrides. The problem is that
you're a doubtful מצורע. Metzora. So once it starts to clear up
here, let it clear up, etc., then what you do is you
do a thing with the birds,
right? You send them out, you know, you dip them in the
thing and you do a גילוח, Giluach, okay, that you do right
at the beginning and then you wait seven days and then you
do another גילוח Giluach
and
a קרבן. Korban.
That's what you do. Four shavings, right?
One, two,
three, four. Okay, now, what does this person have to do? So
here's the story. Why not just, you can't go ahead and just
start by doing this shaving, let's say. Okay, why can't you start
by doing this shaving? You might be a נזיר טהור. Nazir Tahor.
You can't shave in the middle of your נזירות Nezirus of טהרה,
Tahara, you might not be any of these things. So the first
thing you've got to do is you've got to wait 30 days.
Okay, you've waited 30 days. Now, even if you're a נזיר טמא,
Nazir Tamei, okay, you've waited your seven days so you can do
your גילוח Giluach now. If you're a מצורע Metzora you were always
ready to do your גילוח Giluach and even if you're a נזיר
טהור, Nazir Tahor, time to do your גילוח, Giluach, right? So after
30 days you're able to do your first גילוח. Giluach. Okay, got
that? Yes? All right. So now, גילוח Giluach number one.
Now let's say, so assuming you were a נזיר טמא, Nazir Tamei,
okay, you did your first גילוח, Giluach, instead of seven it now
became, you know whatever, it now you waited 30.
You waited 30,
okay, and now you would have to do another 30 days for
טהרה. Tahara. Okay, that's if you were if you're נזיר טמא. Nazir
Tamei. If you're a מצורע Metzora instead of doing it immediately you
waited 30 days to do your גילוח, Giluach, so now,
okay,
you would do your here you would do the birds
and whatever and your other גילוח Giluach and here you would do
your right so you know here you push down your גילוח Giluach
and your קרבן Korban here.
Okay, and now you have seven days to go for the remainder
of it, all right, and then you would do again a גילוח
Giluach and a קרבן. Korban. That's what you should do if you're.
Okay, so that was stage one. Now everybody got in their first
גילוח Giluach as it were, and nothing was violated because you waited
30 days. Now why
now why not go ahead and wait seven days? So the next
thing coming up is a seven days and doing the גילוח Giluach
for this מצורע, Metzora, right? But you can't because you might be
over here and you would violate your נזירות Nezirus of טהרה, Tahara,
right? If you did the גילוח Giluach here at day seven. So
what you have to do is you've got to wait another 30
days.
Okay, and now we've got a גילוח. Giluach. So now for this
guy we're done. If all he was was a נזיר טמא Nazir
Tamei and not a מצורע, Metzora, he did a גילוח giluach here
for נזיר טמא Nazir Tamei and a גילוח giluach here for טהרה.
tahara. We're done for this guy. Okay, but for this and now
for this guy
he did his birds, he waited seventy days, okay? And that seven
days and then down here he does גילוח giluach and קרבן korban
and now we're done with this guy. Okay, so nothing was violated,
we finished with מצורע, Metzora, okay?
So there's two גילוחים giluachim here, right?
At the beginning and then at the end of seven days which
now got pushed off to thirty days.
Right, so that second גילוח giluach sort of double dips for two
purposes, right? The גילוח giluach for the מצורע Metzora with the birds
and also the גילוח giluach for טהור. tahor.
No, because then we would be total no, because then we would
be totally done, but we're not totally done. We're totally done with
this guy because if he was a מצורע, Metzora, you might remember
that being a מצורע Metzora does not count towards your נזירות. nezirus.
Oh, you didn't remember that. Being a מצורע, Metzora, you still have
your full נזירות nezirus to do. If you're ודאי vadai a מצורע,
Metzora, a נזיר מצורע, Nazir Metzora, you still got thirty days of
your נזירות nezirus to do. And if you're ודאי vadai a נזיר
טמא מצורע, Nazir Tamei Metzora, you have to this גילוח giluach here
does not fit you here does not count for your גילוח giluach
of טומאה. tuma. The גמרא Gemara is going to get to that,
but that's implicit here. Okay, so if you're ודאי vadai a נזיר
טמא Nazir Tamei and this גילוח giluach doesn't count for your טומאה,
tuma, so if you're a נזיר טמא מצורע, Nazir Tamei Metzora, this
didn't count, this didn't count, you still need another you need a
גילוח giluach of טומאה tuma and a גילוח giluach of טהרה. tahara.
So why not here do just like I don't know, like I
don't know, wait seven days or something or do another גילוח giluach
of טומאה tuma even if that one didn't count? Because the point
is if you're a נזיר טהור, Nazir Tahor, then your נזירות nezirus
of טהרה tahara basically starts now, okay, and now you need thirty
days. So because you now now this reactivates this section of the
board, okay? And because now you might be at you might be
a נזיר טהור Nazir Tahor and you can't violate that with a
גילוח giluach of נזיר טמא Nazir Tamei assuming you were both, right?
So this is if you were just this. But if you were
this, so from this point on it assumes you are ודאי מצורע
vadai metzora.
and now we're figuring out so now all of this reactivates. So
you've got to wait thirty days here because you might be a
נזיר טהור, Nazir Tahor, okay? So now you waited thirty days, you
did another גילוח giluach because you might be a נזיר טהור, Nazir
Tahor, but you might be a נזיר טמא, Nazir Tamei, right? So
if you're a נזיר טמא, Nazir Tamei, then you did your גילוח
giluach for נזיר טמא. Nazir Tamei. So assuming you were a נזיר
טמא, Nazir Tamei, then you had your first seven days here and
now you're going to get your final thirty days of טהרה tahara
here. All
right, and that's גילוח giluach number four.
If you're a נזיר טמא, Nazir Tamei, why can't you just say
the second day thirty counts for that too? Exactly.
Wait, wait, why can't you say what? This?
No. No, the one over the right. This? No.
Which one? This would be your גילוח giluach for נזיר טמא. Nazir
Tamei.
No, because if it was your גילוח giluach for מצורע, Metzora it
can't count for נזיר Nazir too. Yeah, but why not? That we're
going to get to that, but that's the assumption.
I know, I know, but we're going to get to the idea
that it doesn't double count, okay? Okay, so that's what we're going
to get to. And it doesn't then count. Now that you need
another גילוח, giluach, now that you need another גילוח, giluach,
you can't go ahead and do it because you're now a נזיר
טהור. Nazir Tahor. Okay, so this is the משנה. Mishnah. All right?
So this is at the end of sixty days, right? Sixty days
you're done with your מצורע, Metzora, you can eat קדשים. Kodshim. You
can eat קדשים Kodshim by a נזיר Nazir after seven days after
the ashes of the פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, okay, because and after
a hundred and twenty days you're done with your נזירות, nezirus, all
right? That was the
משנה. Mishnah.
All right? Yes. Quick question, what is this thirty days specifically for
the טהרה? tahara?
Here? טמא. Tamei.
No, just up two more. Those thirty days?
Because if you're a נזיר טמא, Nazir Tamei, you did your you
got out of your טומאה tuma and now you need to do
your נזירות nezirus of טהרה. tahara.
Like a pure נזיר. Nazir.
Oh, the נזירות nezirus of טהרה. tahara.
Yeah, okay.
All right, so let's take a look at the at the גמרא.
Gemara. We'll start from the top. תנא
במה דברים אמורים בנזירות מועטת אבל בנזירות בת שנה, Tanna bameh devarim
amurim binezirus mu'etes aval binezirus bas shanah, if it was a נזירות
nezirus of a year, since all of these gaps are to not
violate right your נזירות nezirus of טהרה, tahara, right? All of these
things are, right? Here it's, right? This is I mean, I don't
know how to indicate it, but it's these it's all because right
here you might be your be doing your נזירות nezirus of טהרה,
tahara, right? Here you might be doing your נזירות nezirus of טהרה.
tahara. Here you might be doing your נזירות nezirus of טהרה, tahara,
here you are doing your נזירות nezirus of טהרה. tahara. All of
the waits are because at any stage you might be in a
נזירות nezirus of טהרה tahara that can't be violated, right? So all
of those gaps, there's thirty-day gaps because of that. So if it
was a נזירות nezirus of a year, you'd have to have year
gaps in order to not violate the נזירות nezirus of טהרה tahara
at any
stage. Okay, אבל בנזירות בת שנה אוכל בקדשים לאחר שתי שנים ושלשים
וששה ימים ומטמא למתים לאחר.
aval binezirus bas shanah ochel
b'kodshim le'achar shtei shanim ushloshim v'shishah yamim umitamei lemeisim le'achar. Now we're
going to talk, he's focusing about the shaving, what are the קרבנות
korbanot that you bring? So in terms of what are the קרבנות
korbanot that you bring, let's talk about what are the קרבנות korbanot
that everybody brings, you know, under
normal—let's not do under normal circumstances. Let's just talk about what are
the ones that can be brought if you're בספק. b'safek. Okay? So
מצורע Metzora, stage one is the birds, right? You dip the birds
in the blood and whatever.
No, well yes, a normal מצורע, metzora but I'm only talking about
the subset of קרבנות korbanot that every person can bring, right, that
could be brought even if you're not sure if you're in that
stage. Okay, you go look in the פסוקים psukim for the whole
full set of the קרבנות. korbanot. Okay? So for a normal מצורע,
metzora, right, the first stage one, when he starts clearing up, they
go out—he's outside the camp—they're not bringing a קרבן, korban, they're slaughtering
a bird, they're, you know, they got the blood, they're dipping it,
they're sprinkling it, whatever. So even if you're not a מצורע, metzora,
I mean okay, you're just doing some weird bird ritual, but anybody
can do it. It's not prohibited to anybody. Okay, at stage two,
that's stage one. Stage two, when he's done with the process and
he brings a קרבן, korban, okay, when he brings this קרבן korban
here, that's the birds, then he brings this קרבן, korban, so the
קרבן korban consists of a what do you call it?
Of a of a bird for חטאת chatat and a bird for
an עולה. olah. So the fact is a you can bring
a חטאת העוף chatat ha'of בספק. b'safek. All right? He brings a
חטאת העוף, chatat ha'of, that's what the תורה torah says, and one
of the קרבנות, korbanot, and if it's brought בספק, b'safek, you're allowed
to bring it בספק b'safek if you don't know. So that's a
קרבן korban that could be brought at stage two that would work
even if you don't know his status. Okay? A
נזיר טמא... nazir tamei...
I'm sorry, I thought the stage two for the מצורע metzora, you're
supposed to be bringing two כבשים kvassim and חטאת אחת chatat achat
and that's it.
Hold on. Is that not a case about a poor person? Oh,
about a poor person.
ואם דל הוא, v'im dahl hu, ואין ידו משגת, v'ein yado maseget,
ולקח
כבש אחד אשם לתנופה לכפר, v'lakach keves echad asham l'tnufah l'chaper, ואיסר
סולת בלול, v'isar solet balul, ושתי תורים או שני בני יונה, u-shtei
torim o shnei b'nei yonah, אחד לחטאת ואחד
לעולה. echad l'chatat v'echad l'olah. Okay,
so the yeah,
so basically the whole discussion like that you have to write up,
you know, all of his property in his spouse's—in his wife's or
husband's name so that he can be poor. I'm serious, I'm tech—serious.
But it's a good point. Okay, if he's poor, okay, if he's
poor,
he brings a חטאת העוף. chatat ha'of. Now he also brings an
עולת העוף, olat ha'of, so there's a question why not bring that
בספק? b'safek? Okay? And he also brings an אשם, asham, and I
should say the אשם asham is going to be a is going
to be a question in the גמרא gemara because the אשם asham
is actually needed for the מצורע metzora and we're going to be
ignoring the אשם. asham. So that is going to be a problem.
But the חטאת העוף chatat ha'of can definitely be brought בספק. b'safek.
Okay?
נזיר טמא, nazir tamei, what does a נזיר טמא nazir tamei bring?
He also brings an עולת העוף olat ha'of and a חטאת העוף.
chatat ha'of. Okay, you
might—Michael can check if that's only if he's poor again, I forget.
Okay? That can be brought בספק. b'safek. And a normal נזיר nazir
brings an עולה, olah, חטאת, chatat, and a שלמים. shlamim. Okay, for
some reason we're also going to ignore the שלמים, shlamim, but an
עולה olah can definitely be brought בתנאי. b'tnai. Either it's my עולה,
olah, my obligatory עולה, olah, or it's a or it's a gift,
it's a סתם stam עולת נדבה. olat nedavah. Okay, so these are
the various קרבנות, korbanot, but these things, the birds, the חטאת העוף
chatat ha'of can be brought בספק b'safek and an עולה olah can
be brought בתנאי. b'tnai. Okay, those are the things that could be
brought even when you don't know what your status
is because the תורה torah allows—a normal חטאת chatat can't be brought
בספק, b'safek, but it allows a חטאת העוף chatat ha'of to be.
An עולה olah can be either an obligation or a gift. And
the ציפורים tzippurim is just some ritual outside the בית המקדש. beit
hamikdash. Okay, so now at each stage you're going to bring the
קרבנות korbanot that are that are possible to be brought. Okay? And
the reason is, the reason you have to bring these קרבנות korbanot
like at each stage, by the way, is in order to do
the גילוח, giluach, in order to move on to the next stage
you need to bring some minimal קרבן, korban, right? A נזיר טמא
nazir tamei can't move on to being a נזיר טהור nazir tahor
unless he brings a minimal קרבן. korban. A נזיר טהור nazir tahor
doesn't finish his נזירות nezirut unless he brings a minimal קרבן. korban.
Right? A מצורע metzora doesn't move on to the next stage or
doesn't become טהור tahor unless he brings a minimal קרבן. korban. So
since you need to move on to the next stage here, that's
the whole point, at each stage you have to bring based on
what stage—status—you might be at, a minimal set of קרבנות. korbanot.
Did you also bring a שלמים shlamim too?
Yeah, so that's the question why it's not going to mention the
שלמים shlamim and the עולת העוף. olat ha'of. Okay, I don't know,
but let's not worry about that right now.
Quick quick question, yes, so meanwhile with this מצורע, metzora this is...
we've just waited four years for the whole thing. Two years ago
he got the צרעת, Tzara'at, right? Right. So I mean just like
bring this contextually, so meanwhile this guy is sitting out in some
sort of מצורע Metzora, camp for two years, away from his whole
family? Well, yeah.
And he's not eating קרבן פסח Korban Pesach yet. Alright, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Yeah, get his נזירות Nezirut undone,
we'll speed things up.
Yes, does the נזיר טמא... Nazir Tamei... a lamb אשם Asham becomes
a ודאי? vadai Wait, נזיר טמא... Nazir Tamei... ודאי? Vadai? Yeah, it
becomes a question, yeah, it becomes a question of
a ודאי. Vadai?
Yeah, well we're not discussing the אשם, Asham, what what will happen
to it. Okay, I mean but well, no, it will never be
a ודאי, Vadai. he can't bring it. Okay, whether you can bring
an אשם בספק Asham Besafek you might be able to do and
we'll get to. Yeah, we're going to get to that. Okay. So
yeah, but that's true, נזיר טמא Nazir Tamei also brings an אשם.
Asham.
Like a חטאת Chatat for the אשם? Asham?
No, an אשם Asham is a little bit more flexible than a
חטאת. Chatat. Okay, and we're actually going to see about that. Okay,
but for now we're assuming that. So let's take a look at
the ברייתא. Braita. דתניא עלה: Detanya Ala: ומגלח ארבע תגלחיות. Umegalei'ach Arba
Tiglachyot. תגלחת ראשונה מביא ציפורים וחטאת העוף עולת בהמה. Tiglachat Rishona mevi
tziporim vechatat ha'of olat behema.
So this first one you might be any of the three categories,
right? You might be finished stage one of מצורע, Metzora well you're
not stage two, finished stage one of מצורע Metzora, or finished a
נזיר טמא Nazir Tamei or being a נזיר טהור. Nazir Tahor. Is
that clear? So if you can be any one of the three,
what do you bring? So ציפורים tziporim because of stage one of
the מצורע, Metzora חטאת העוף chatat ha'of because of נזיר טמא, Nazir
Tamei, and עולת בהמה olat behema because of נזיר טהור, Nazir Tahor,
that's at stage one.
Why don't you bring a שלמים Shelamim like you talked about?
Alright, let's summary.
He brings an עולת בהמה olat behema even if it's a ספק
safek situation?
It's an עולה, olah, that's what I'm saying, it's not a חטאת,
chatat, it's an עולה. olah. שניה, Shniya, stage two. So what are
you possibly here at stage two? You're not a נזיר טהור. Nazir
Tahor. If you were a נזיר טהור Nazir Tahor you were done
at stage one, right? So at stage two, the only two possibilities
you are are... I'm sorry, I said that wrong. If you were
נזיר... Nazir... if you were נזיר טהור Nazir Tahor you're done at
stage one, if you were נזיר טמא Nazir Tamei you did your
טומאה tumah stage one, so at stage two you're a נזיר... Nazir...
it's your נזיר טהור. Nazir Tahor. Everybody with me? And if you
were מצורע Metzora, you did your stage one here so you're stage
two מצורע. Metzora So at stage two you're either finishing נזיר טהור
Nazir Tahor or finishing מצורע. Metzora. Yes?
Okay.
So you
don't do the תגלחת tiglachat and the bird thing at seven days,
you have to wait till the thirty days for the נזיר טמא
Nazir Tamei there, right?
Yeah, everything is waiting thirty days because you might... because of the
נזיר טהור Nazir Tahor makes you wait. Okay, we did that, right.
So anyway so here if you were נזיר טהור Nazir Tahor you're
totally done. If you were נזיר טמא Nazir Tamei by stage two
now you're ending a נזירות טהרה. nezirut tahara. And if you were
מצורע Metzora. now you're ending a מצורע. Metzora So נזיר טהור Nazir
Tahor and מצורע Metzora. stage two is חטאת העוף ועולת בהמה. chatat
ha'of ve'olat behema.
Alright? חטאת העוף ועולת בהמה. Chatat ha'of ve'olat behema. שלישית, Shlishit, stage
three. So at stage three מצורע Metzora is off the table, now
we're only looking at נזירות nezirut starting again. So at stage three
you're either ending a נזירות טהרה nezirut tahara or ending a נזירות
טומאה. nezirut tumah. Okay? So stage three מביא חטאת העוף mevi chatat
ha'of for נזירות טומאה nezirut tumah and עולת בהמה olat behema because
נזיר טהור. Nazir Tahor. Stage four, the only thing left is נזירות
טהרה. nezirut tahara. רביעית Revi'it מביא קרבן טהרה. mevi korban tahara. So
not only do you bring... you bring the full קרבן טהרה korban
tahara because now you're def... the one thing you definitely are now
and you definitely have been is a נזיר. Nazir. So the נזיר
Nazir קרבן korban you'll bring in full. And in case you had
brought the עולה Olah earlier, fine, the עולה Olah of the whole
קרבן korban will be בתנאי, bitnai, but the rest of the קרבן
korban you'll bring completely.
So at the end of that final stage you're bringing three קרבנות?
korbanot?
Yes, you're bringing the whole thing and you say if I've brought
the עולה Olah before, then that counts and this is the remainder,
and otherwise this is everything.
It's like it was a נדבה nedava
as it were, a נדבה. nedava. Correct. And now the גמרא Gemara
works that all out. See, I just... so אמרת, amarta, so the
rest of the גמרא Gemara is just going to be saying in
words what we said out loud... what we said outside. אמרת: Amarta:
תגלחת ראשונה מביא... tiglachat rishona mevi... ממה נפשך. mima nafshach.
So the first shaving, it's one of each, ממה נפשך. mima nafshach.
שפיר
קא מייתי. Shapir ka mayti. It's all good as you bring one
of each collection. דאי ודאי מצורע הוא, De'ee vadai metzora hu, if
he was a מצורע Metzora stage one, ולאו טמא הוא, velav tamei
hu, and not a טמא... tamei... he wasn't a טמא, tamei, I
mean not a נזיר טמא, Nazir Tamei, meaning even if he is
a טמא tamei but he's also a מצורע, metzora if he's definitely
a מצורע, metzora, so what קרבן korban do you have to bring
as a מצורע? metzora, ציפורים חובתו. Tziporim chovato. And not a קרבן,
korban, what you do is you do the bird ritual if it's
מצורע metzora? stage one.
Did you remind us what's... there's two birds in that?
Yeah, one's slaughtered and the other is dipped with a
brush and you dip?
Exactly, exactly. Okay. And let it fly away? Exactly.
Okay. ציפורי חובתו. tziporei chovato. So if you're a מצורע, metzora the
other stuff is not on the table now, you do stage one
of מצורע, metzora, which is the bird ritual, וחטאת העוף ספק, vechatat
ha'of safek, and the חטאת העוף chatat ha'of which you brought because
you might be a נזיר טמא, nazir tamei, fine, you're allowed to
bring it בספק, besafek, ואזיל לקבורה, ve'azil likvurah, it would be buried
because that's what you do when you don't know with a חטאת,
chatat, you sprinkle the blood and you bury the bird. ועולה הוי
נדבה, ve'olah havi nedavah, and the עולה olah because you might have
been a נזיר טהור, nazir tahor, now is counts for just a
free will עולה. olah. Okay. ולגלחו תוך שבע עכשיו? ulgalcho toch sheva
achshav? That if you were a מצורע, metzora, why don't we just
shave you right away, even within seven days or within thirty days,
why are we waiting? You can't do that. דלמא לאו מצורע הוא,
dilma lav metzora hu, maybe you're not a מצורע, metzora, ורחמנא אמר
verachmana amar תער לא יעבור על ראשו. ta'ar lo ya'avor al rosho.
As a נזיר nazir you can't shave, you might be in your
normal נזירות טהרה, nezirus tahara, you can't shave, so that's why you
had to wait thirty days, עד מלאות. ad melot. Okay. So
that's if you were a ודאי Vadai, מצורע. metzora, Yes, but you're
not. Okay. ואי לאו מצורע ודאי הוי, ve'i lav metzora vadai havi,
so if you weren't a מצורע, metzora, והוא טמא, vehu tamei, but
you are נזיר טמא, nazir tamei, so חטאת העוף חובתו, chatat ha'of
chovato, so נזיר טמא nazir tamei you're bringing your חטאת העוף, chatat
ha'of, that worked actually, והציפורין vehatziporin and the bird ritual that you're
doing now, אבראי קא מיתעבדין, avra'i ka mita'avdin, they're done outside the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. ולא הוי חולין בעזרה, velo havi chulin ba'azarah,
it's not a קרבן korban in the עזרה, azarah, it's just a
weird ritual. It's a מצורע metzora ritual that you didn't need to
do, but whatever, it's not a קרבן. korban. ועולת בהמה הוי נדבה,
ve'olas behemah havi nedavah, and the עולת בהמה olas behemah is a
נדבה. nedavah. So that's why, right, so, so if you are נזיר
טמא, nazir tamei, the חטאת העוף chatat ha'of worked for you, and
the rest you're good. It's a נדבה, nedavah, it's a weird ritual,
doesn't, it's fine to do it. ואי לאו מצורע הוא ולאו טמא
הוא, ve'i lav metzora hu velav tamei hu, and if you aren't
a מצורע metzora and you weren't a טמא, tamei, this is all
still at stage one, וציפורין אבראי קא מיתעבדין, vetziporin avra'i ka mita'avdin,
the bird ritual is outside the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, no harm,
no foul. חטאת העוף לקבורה, chatat ha'of likvurah, the חטאת העוף chatat
ha'of that you did because you might have been a נזיר טמא
nazir tamei is, okay, that was בספק, besafek, so it's going to
be buried, and you're allowed to bring it בספק. besafek. ועולת בהמה
הוי חובתו, ve'olas behemah havi chovato, ועולת בהמה olas behemah is your
חובה. chovah. So basically you just worked through why do you have
at stage one here ציפורין, tziporin, חטאת העוף, chatat ha'of, and עולה,
olah, because that counts, that will cover you for all the possible
things you're at stage one. Let's break down that stage one. What?
What you bring?
Yeah, ציפורין, tziporin, stage one.
חטאת העוף chatat ha'of and עולה. olah.
Then stage two.
Stage two is, let's work it out, it's חטאת העוף chatat ha'of
and עולת בהמה. olas behemah.
Wait, חטאת העוף chatat ha'of and עולה.
olah. חטאת העוף chatat ha'of and עולה. olah.
Then stage three.
Yeah, but for a different reason, חטאת העוף chatat ha'of and עולה,
olah, and this is full קרבן טהרה. korban tahara.
Okay,
so basically just worked through stage one and stage one, right, you
might be מצורע metzora stage one, you might be נזיר טמא, nazir
tamei, you might be נזיר טהור. nazir tahor. Okay. Stage two, you
might be מצורע metzora stage two or נזיר טהור. nazir tahor. Stage
three, you might be נזיר טמא nazir tamei or נזיר טהור, nazir
tahor, and here you're נזיר טהור. nazir tahor. Okay, so it all
works. Now, הגמרא hagmarah says like this, דבעי אשם, deba'ei asham, so
it doesn't work, so one minute, says הגמרא, hagmarah, you need an
אשם. asham. Now really you need an אשם asham is not a
question now because, well it could be for נזיר טמא, nazir tamei,
but the אשם asham for נזיר טמא nazir tamei is not מעכב.
me'akev. But the אשם asham for מצורע metzora is מעכב. me'akev. Another
גמרא gmarah says that the אשם, asham, only the אשם asham really
counts as his כפרה kaparah for a, for a מצורע metzora in
order to מטהר metaher him. So it says here חטאת העוף chatat
ha'of should not be enough. That's nice that he brought a קרבן,
korban, but here at stage two the מצורע metzora needs an אשם
asham and that hasn't been mentioned. So הגמרא hagmarah says דבי שמעוני
דאמר מייתי ומתני. debei Shimoni de'amar maysei umasni. Yes, there's a position
of רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon that says that you can stipulate, bring
an אשם בתנאי, asham betnai, and say if it's not an אשם,
asham, it's a שלמים. shelamim. The reason he says a שלמים shelamim
is because it's the same animal that's used, okay, or whatever, that's
a special הלכה halacha that the מותר אשם mosar asham קרב שלמים.
karev shelamim. Alright, so basically, so הגמרא hagmarah now, so הגמרא hagmarah
says yes, a מצורע metzora needed an אשם, asham, it wasn't mentioned
in the ברייתא, braisa, which is strange, it's not answering why it's
not mentioned, it's just saying how we solve the problem and you
solve the problem according to רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon that says you
can bring an אשם בתנאי, asham betnai, which is all very lovely,
but if you don't פוסק pasken like רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, how
does this guy ever get out of this state? I don't know
what the answer to that is. Okay, so now, תגלחת שנייה ושלישית.
tiglachas shniya ushlishis. So
we, we interrupt talking about number one with the אשם, asham, which
is bizarre, because the real necessity of the אשם asham is for
the מצורע. metzora. I mean there is an אשם asham for נזיר
טמא, nazir tamei, but it's not necessary. The real necessity is מצורע.
metzora. Anyway, now we go to the rest of the, to stage
two and stage three. ציפורין לא צריך, tziporin lo tzarich, at stage
two and stage three you no longer need the birds, you only
needed the birds only, only at stage one would that have been
the, only you know, at shaving one would that have been stage
one of מצורע. metzora. After shaving one you're done with stage one
of מצורע, metzora, so birds are no longer part of the discussion.
דהא עביד, deha avid, so because you did the birds at the
first shaving. That would have been, then you would have been done
with it. מאי איכא? mai ikka? So what's left now? What are
the possibilities now at stage two?
ודאי מוחלט? vadai muchlat? מאי איכא דילמא ודאי מוחלט? mai ikka dilma
vadai muchlat? You gotta love that, maybe he's definitely a מוחלט. muchlat.
Okay, so חדא לספק ספרו וחדא לספק טומאתו. hada l'safek sipro v'hada
l'safek tumato.
So here, it's really talking about stage two, not stage three. Here,
okay, you as a מצורע, metzora, you won't need the birds anymore,
you already did that. So you have one for ספק ספרו, safek
sipro, which is the חטאת העוף, chatas ha'of, which is stage two
of מצורע. metzora. And one for, and so that's זבח חטאת העוף
zivch chatas ha'of meaning the עולה olah in both of these cases
is for נזיר טהור. nazir tahor. Okay, but the חטאת העוף chatas
ha'of in stage two is because you might be ending מצורע, metzora,
that's ספק מוחלט. safek muchlat. And the חטאת chatas in stage three
is because you might be ending
טומאה, tum'a, נזיר טמא. nazir tamei. חדא לספק ספרו וחדא לספק טומאתו.
hada l'safek sipro v'hada l'safek tumato. Okay, and the עולה olah in
both cases is because you might be ending נזירות טהרה. nezirus tahara.
תגלחת רביעית מביא קרבן טהור ומתני. tigrachas revi'is meivi korban tahor v'masni.
And the last one, all that's left with it is a קרבן
טהור, korban tahor, so you're bringing the full קרבן korban and you
stipulate. And what do you stipulate? You say like this: אי ודאי
נזיר הוא, i vadai nazir hu, so עולה ראשונה חובה וזו נדבה.
olah rishona chova v'zu nedava.
If I was a נזיר nazir earlier, if I was a נזיר
טהור nazir tahor at one of the earlier stages, then the animal
I brought at whatever earlier stage that was that I was a
נזיר טהור nazir tahor was my obligatory, and this עולה olah is
a נדבה. nedava. ואם טמא ומוחלט הוא, v'im tamei u'muchlat hu, but
if I was in this category or this category, and only now
am I doing my נזירות טהרה, nezirus tahara, then עולה ראשונה נדבה,
olah rishona nedava, anything I gave earlier was a free-will sacrifice, וזו
חובה, v'zu chova, and this עולה olah is the obligatory. So as
far as the עולה, olah, right, the full one is the עולה,
olah,
the חטאת, chatas, and the שלמים. shelamim. So basically he says, as
far as the עולה olah is concerned, if I brought it before,
if I did my נזירות טהרה nezirus tahara before, that then those
were, that was my obligatory עולה olah and this is, this is
a נדבה. nedava. If only now I'm doing my נזירות טהרה, nezirus
tahara, then this is my obligation. But either way these two are
the remainder of my obligation, right, because even if I brought my
obligatory עולה olah earlier and I was a נזיר טהור nazir tahor
earlier, I never finished bringing the rest of my sacrifice. Okay, וזה
שאר קרבנו. v'ze sha'ar korbano.
And this is the remainder of the קרבן. korban. So that's working
the whole thing out. Now, by the way, תוספות Tosafos does raise
the question, I should just say, which is we asked the issue
about bringing an אשם Asham here, which is necessary, and it's not
so clear that you could bring an אשם בתנאי Asham b'tenai and
what do you do if you don't פסקן pasken that way? But
the other question to be asked, right, is why not bring an
עולת העוף olas ha'of at various cases? You can bring an עולת
העוף olas ha'of and make a stipulation, either it's an obligation or
it's a נדבה. nedava. It's an עולה, olah, right? Why not bring
a שלמים shelamim at the various stages and make a stipulation, right?
So, you know, so תוספות Tosafos basically says like we, you know,
because there are all these ספקות sfekot around, we really want to
just do what is sort of minimally required to be יוצא. yotze.
We don't want to bring, what would you gain by bringing...
Then you could say that if I was a נזיר טמא, nazir
tamei, I brought more of my obligatory קרבן, korban, but you know
you'd have to, but anyway, but it's clear what we're trying to
do is do the very, basically do the bare minimum. Okay, now
as if that wasn't fun enough, we get to do with other
things which are actually less complicated when here you're ספק safek everything.
What if you're ודאי vadai one of them and ספק safek the
other? Okay, it should be, from this point on it should be,
it should be easy, it should be easy. I mean come on,
we've done the most complicated situation. Okay, so it says...
But the term מוחלט muchlat only refers to a מצורע, metzora, right?
What?
The term מוחלט muchlat is only מצורע ודאי. metzora vadai. Yeah, exactly.
Exactly. Okay, now, let's say you're טמא ספק ומוחלט ודאי. tamei safek
u'muchlat vadai. Okay, you're definitely a מצורע, metzora, but maybe
טמא מת, tamei mes, a נזיר טמא מת. nazir tamei mes. So
אוכל בקדשים לאחר שמונה ימים, ochel b'kodashim l'achar shmona yamim, ושותה יין
ומיטמא למתים לאחר שישה ושבעים ימים. v'shosei yayin v'mitamei l'mesim l'achar shisha
v'shiv'im yamim.
So what do you do? You are a מצורע ודאי. metzora vadai.
Because you are a מצורע ודאי, metzora vadai, okay, you basically, as
a מצורע, metzora, if you're a נזיר מצורע, nazir metzora, if you
know you're מצורע, metzora, then the shaving, you know, goes, you know,
violates the נזירות, nezirus, because if you're definitely a מצורע metzora you
do it even though you're a נזיר. nazir. Okay, so if you're
מצורע ודאי, metzora vadai, so you shave, okay, at the beginning when
you find out, and then you wait seven days and you shave
again, even though you're מצורע, metzora, okay, that's what a מצורע metzora
does, right? If you're מצורע ודאי. metzora vadai. Now, now what do
you do? Well, now you're back into the state about being a
נזיר ספק טמא. nazir safek tamei. So because you're ספק טמא, safek
tamei, if you're ודאי טמא, vadai tamei, what you would do is
you'd wait seven days, okay, this is the end, that's מצורע. metzora.
Okay, now if you're ודאי טמא, vadai tamei, if you're טמא, tamei,
you'd wait seven days and shave, right? And then, you might not
even have to wait seven days because whatever... Anyway, yeah, but you
would shave right away. But because you might be טהור Tahor or
not טמא, Tamei, you can't shave for the טומאה Tumah after seven,
you have to end your נזירות Nezirut of טהרה Tahara and in
order to do the shaving because you might be טמא. Tamei. So
you wait thirty days, and then you shave because you're ספק טמא.
Safek Tamei. Okay, and then, if you were טמא, Tamei, then you
wait another thirty days as your טהרה. Tahara. Okay, so, yeah, clear?
If you weren't טמא Tamei you could have basically, you know, waited
seven days or something and done it, but now you have to
do the whole thing. So that's sixty-seven days, which is what it
says. Okay. אוכל בקדשים אחר שמונים יום, Ochel bekodshim achar shmonim yom,
after eight. The reason it says eight is because
you bring the קרבן Korban on day eight. All right, so don't
get caught up by that. רישינו לא מטמא לאחר ששים ושבעה ימים.
Reisha'einu lo metamei l'achar shishim v'shiva yamim. מצורע ספק וטמא ודאי. Metzora
Safek v'Tamei Vadai.
Let's say you're possibly a מצורע, Metzora, but you're definitely נזיר טמא.
Nazir Tamei. So again, if you're possibly מצורע Metzora the first thing
you've got to do is get out of the status of being
מצורע. Metzora. But you have to wait... the first waiting, you can't
shave right away because, right, you're possibly a מצורע, Metzora, but you're
possibly a... even a נזיר טמא Nazir Tamei can't shave if it's
not sort of part of the נזירות, Nezirut, okay, but what you
can do is the following: If you're definitely a טמא Tamei and
possibly a מצורע, Metzora, wait seven days. Okay. Now, if you've waited
seven days, since you're definitely a טמא, Tamei, so you're allowed to
shave here because as a נזיר טמא Nazir Tamei you're definitely a
נזיר טמא Nazir Tamei who can shave after seven... after seven days,
right? Yes, a נזיר טמא Nazir Tamei shaves after seven days, right?
And if you were a מצורע, Metzora, you don't know, you're questionable
מצורע, Metzora, but you can do shaving number one of a
questionable מצורע Metzora because you're shaving anyway as a נזיר טמא. Nazir
Tamei. Okay? So because you're a נזיר טמא Nazir Tamei you only
had to wait seven days as opposed to... you might have been...
you're definitely a נזיר טמא, Nazir Tamei, so you know at the
end of seven days you can shave and that counts as shaving
one of a מצורע. Metzora.
But that earlier didn't work with the מצורע Metzora and the נזיר
טמא Nazir Tamei because
you were ספק טמא Safek Tamei here. So in case you were
נזיר טהור, Nazir Tahor, you can't shave after seven days.
But once you are shaving...
once you are shaving as a נזיר טמא, Nazir Tamei, then you
could say either this is the shaving for a נזיר טמא, Nazir
Tamei, right, or shaving for מצורע. Metzora.
But after that, you
couldn't shave here because you might have been...
Day two? But after you wait the thirty days and you're shaving
for your ספק טמא, Safek Tamei, it doesn't count.
I didn't say it's counted. It's going to count only for one
here, but you are allowed to shave. If you're... if you're מצורע
Metzora it doesn't count... it doesn't count for your טומאה. Tumah. You're
allowed to shave because either you're shaving as טמא Tamei or you're
shaving as מצורע. Metzora. It's not going to count for both.
But what I don't understand is one of them here was ודאי.
Vadai. So how can you make a תנאי Tenai if this, that,
or that? You know you have a ודאי. Vadai.
If I am a מצורע, Metzora, then you have to deal with
צרעת Tzara'at before you deal with the טומאה. Tumah. Okay. If I'm
a מצורע, Metzora, this counts as... as... as for my shaving for
מצורע. Metzora. If I'm not a מצורע, Metzora, it counts as shaving
for being a נזיר טמא. Nazir Tamei. I'm definitely a נזיר טמא,
Nazir Tamei, but if it takes מצורע, Metzora, that takes precedence.
Yeah, okay.
So that's what you do there. Now, you've got to do shaving
number two for מצורע, Metzora, okay? Now shaving number two for מצורע,
Metzora, let's figure it out. If you were a טמא, Tamei, that
counted, so now you're going to have to... you can't shave within
seven days because if you're טמא, Tamei, now you have to start
your נזירות Nezirut of טהרה. Tahara. You have to wait thirty. So
you have to wait thirty and to do shaving number two for
a ספק מצורע. Safek Metzora.
Because that seven was inside the thirty. It's not thirty-seven?
No, because if you're... yes it is thirty-seven. If you're נזיר טמא,
Nazir Tamei, you wait seven days and shave and thirty days and
shave again for your טהרה. Tahara.
Shaving days aren't counting towards your נזירות.
Nezirut. That's הלכה. Halakha. You wait seven days to become טהור, Tahor,
you shave, you do... bring your קרבן, Korban, you restart your נזירות
Nezirut of טהרה. Tahara. Right. Okay.
So... okay. So
you've got that. You were ספק מצורע Safek Metzora and you were
able to do that in thirty-seven days.
So you're shaving at thirty-seven.
You're shaving at seven and at... right, this is a total of
thirty-seven. Okay. All right. So now, too good. You're good for מצורע.
Metzora. Now, if you were a מצורע, Metzora, only now can you
start worrying about your status of being a נזיר טמא. Nazir Tamei.
You can't... this does not double count as... correct. So therefore now
you have to start worrying about seven and do your shaving for
טמא Tamei and thirty and do your shaving for טהרה, Tahara, okay,
so you're going to get a total of seventy-four days. Thirty-seven, thirty-seven.
Yes. All right.
Trust me on it. All right. That seven was the last seven
was for a definite מצורע? Metzora?
This is if he was a definite מצורע, Metzora,
right.
Let's take a look. מוחלט ספק וטמא ודאי, muchlat safeik v'tamei vaday,
אוכל בקדשים לאחר שלושים ושבעה ימים. ochel b'kodshim l'achar shloshim v'shivah yamim.
After 37 days you're out of your מצורע metzora status, which is
your possible מצורע metzora status, and you can eat קדשים. kodshim. ושלשים
וארבעה וטמא למתים לאחר שבעים וארבעה ימים. v'shloshim v'arba'ah v'tamei l'metim l'achar
shivim v'arba'ah yamim. And after and after 74 days you can go
ahead and you're totally out of everything. And the simplest case is:
טמא ודאי ומוחלט ודאי, tamei vaday u'muchlat vaday, you're ודאי vaday a
נזיר טמא nazir tamei and you're ודאי vaday a מוחלט. muchlat. So,
אוכל בקדשים לאחר שמונה ימים, ochel b'kodshim l'achar shmonah yamim, then you
don't have to wait. You shaved shaving one for מצורע metzora on
day one, shaving two on day seven, you bring your קרבן korban
on day eight for מצורע, metzora, so you eat קדשים kodshim after
eight days. And then you do your next 37 days. Seven days
for טומאה, tumah, 30 days for טהרה, taharah, and you're done. Okay?
So you did that לאחר שמונה ימים ושלשים וארבעה וטמא למתים לאחר
ארבעים וארבעה ימים, l'achar shmonah yamim v'shloshim v'arba'ah v'tamei l'metim l'achar arbaim
v'arba'ah yamim, right? Seven days for one and then you start on
day eight the next process, 37 days, seven and 30, 44 days.
Okay, we got through that. יישר כח shkoyach everyone! Now it gets
easy. Okay, שאלו תלמידיו את רבי שמעון בן יוחאי. sha'alu talmidav et
Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai. This is a fun תוספתא. tosefta. רבי שמעון
בן יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai's students asked him, this is going
to be the question people ask: why can't certain of the shavings
double count? Okay? So נזיר טהור ומצורע מהו שיגלח תגלחת אחת ועולה
לו לכאן ולכאן. nazir tahor u'metzora mahu she'yigale'ach tiglachat achat v'olah lo
l'kan u'l'kan. So if you've got a guy who is a נזיר
טהור, nazir tahor, meaning he's not טמא מת, tamei met, and he's
a מצורע, metzora, why doesn't the shaving count for both? Okay? So
meaning, not even our complicated case, let's say I was a נזיר
טהור nazir tahor and my 30 days were up because the מצורע
metzora period doesn't count towards נזירות, nezirut, you might remember. Let's say
my 30 days were up. Okay? And then ממש mamash right before
I got a chance to, you know, to whatever, to go to
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash to do the whole thing, I became
a מצורע, metzora, alright? So then, why when that מצורע metzora period
is over and I do that shaving, let that shaving double count?
Okay? For just the מצוה mitzvah of shaving, let it double count.
Again, implicit in here, I'm not going to unpack this, but as
you were asking and realizing, implicit in this whole thing is none
of the shavings double count. But that's what they're asking: why can't
it? Okay? נזיר טהור ומצורע מהו שיגלח תגלחת אחת ועולה לו לכאן
ולכאן. nazir tahor u'metzora mahu she'yigale'ach tiglachat achat v'olah lo l'kan u'l'kan.
אמר להם, amar lahem, he said to them: אינו מגלח. eino megale'ach.
No. Okay. אמרו לו, amru lo, they said to him: למה? lamah?
אמר להם: amar lahem: אילו זה לגדל וזה לגדל וזה להעביר וזה
להעביר, ilu zeh l'gadel v'zeh l'gadel v'zeh l'ha'avir v'zeh l'ha'avir, if they
were doing the same thing, one of them was functioning to grow
the hair again and the other to grow the hair again, and
they were both functioning to take the hair off, יפה אתם אומרים,
yafeh atem omrim, then they would be similar. עכשיו נזיר להעביר ומצורע
לגדל. achshav nazir l'ha'avir u'metzora l'gadel.
The נזיר nazir is to is to get it remove it and
the מצורע metzora is to grow it. Now what does that mean?
What that means is, we're running out of space on the board.
This is so gorgeous, I don't want I want oh, sorry. Alright,
Zellon you wanted?
Okay.
Everything's clear? Everything's clear. Okay.
So then, so we use this part. Okay, so let's talk about
what the what they do. Okay? What does a מצורע metzora do?
It says, let's go ahead and read the פסוקים psukim actually. Imagine
that, reading the פסוקים. psukim.
Oh, alright, fine. I appreciate it. I'll find it. Okay. It says
like this. It says, here's what he does, it clears up, and
it says like this: וצוה הכהן ולקח למטהר שתי צפרים v'tzivah hakohen
v'lakach l'mitahar shtei tziporim blah blah blah, excuse me. חס
ושלום. chas v'shalom.
Oh, we gotta edit that out. Oh my God. Okay. שתי צפרים,
shtei tziporim, I'm sorry, etc. וכולי וגו', v'chulei v'gomer, חיות טהורות ועץ
ארז ושני תולעת ואזוב. chayot tehorot v'etz erez u'shni tolaat v'ezov. Okay,
he does the whole thing with the birds. Okay? And then it
says, and he sprinkles it, והזה על המטהר. v'hizah al hamitahar. Okay.
וכבס המטהר את בגדיו וגלח את כל שערו, v'kibes hamitahar et bgadav
v'gilach et kol se'aro, גלח, gilach, okay, את כל שערו ורחץ
במים,
et kol se'aro v'rachatz
b'mayim, which is מקוה, mikvah, ורחץ במים, v'rachatz b'mayim, okay, so that's
מקוה, mikvah, that will be day one or whatever, וטהר ואחר יבא
אל המחנה וישב מחוץ לאהלו שבעת ימים, v'taher v'achar yavo el hamachaneh
v'yashav michutz l'ohalo shivat yamim, then seven, okay, days. Okay? וביום השביעי
יגלח את כל שערו, u'vayom hashvi'i yigalach et kol se'aro, so on
day seven it's יגלח yigalach again, גילוח, giluach, גלח, galach, okay, גילוח,
giluach, את ראשו וכבס את בגדיו ורחץ את בשרו במים וטהר. et
rosho v'kibes et bgadav v'rachatz et bsharo b'mayim v'taher. So again, מקוה,
mikvah, וכבס את בגדיו, v'kibes et bgadav, מקוה. mikvah. And that's on
day seven. וביום השמיני, u'vayom hashmini, and then on day eight, he
brings his קרבן. korban. Okay, that's the מצורע. metzora. נזיר, nazir, what
does a נזיר nazir do? The נזיר טמא. nazir tamei. Starting with
נזיר טמא. nazir tamei. Well, okay, נזיר, nazir, well we'll start with
טמא tamei and then we'll get to טהור. tahor. So נזיר nazir
is okay, here we go. וכי ימות מת עליו בפתע פתאם וטמא
ראש נזרו וגלח ביום טהרתו ביום השביעי. v'chi yamut met alav b'feta
pitom v'tamei rosh nizro v'gilach b'yom taharato b'yom hashvi'i. So, seven days.
of טהרה, taharah, and then it's גילח, gilach, okay, גילוח. giluach. ביום
השביעי יגלחנו. B'yom hashvi'i yiglachenu. וביום השמיני יביא, U'v'yom hashmini yavi, and
then on day eight is a קרבן. korban. Okay. Then he goes
30 days as טהור, tahor, okay, or if he just started as
טהור, tahor, what does he do on day 30 as טהור? tahor?
Then it says he's done, yes, and then וזאת תורת הנזיר ביום
מלאת לו יביא פתח אהל מועד והקריב קרבנו להשם כבש בן שנתו
וסלת מצה והקריב לפני השם ואת האיל יעשה וגילח. V'zos toras hanazir
b'yom milos lo yavi pesach ohel moed v'hikriv korbano laHashem keves ben
shnaso v'soles matzah v'hikriv lifnei Hashem v'es ha'ayil ya'aseh v'gilach. So it's
all the קרבנות, korbanos, all the קרבנות, korbanos, and then גילוח. giluach.
Okay, the גילוח giluach comes after all the קרבנות, korbanos, okay. Someone
also said that you know maybe one of them may be... I
understand but that's not our interest right now. So now we're going
to point out how all of these גילוחים giluachim are slightly different
from one another. Okay. So the first question was, what was the
first question? The first question was, נזיר טהור מצורע. nazir tahor metzora.
Okay, נזיר טהור nazir tahor and מצורע. metzora. So he says אילו
זה נזיר טהור מצורע. Ilu zeh nazir tahor metzora. So he says
this one is לגדל. legadel. What does it mean this is לגדל?
legadel? That the hair has to grow back for a second גילוח.
giluach. This one you're done, this one you shave and you're done.
That's considered להעביר. leha'avir. You get the hair off and you're done.
This is getting it off as part of a process of it
growing again and shaving again. That makes more sense you could just
say just don't shave. Well but he's saying they're not doing the
same thing, they're not functioning in the same way, okay. So מבעיא
דמבעיא
אשכח נזיר להעביר מצורע לגדל.
Miba'aya
d'miba'aya
ashkech nazir leha'avir metzora legadel.
Okay so now it says the next question. ולא תעלה לו ימי
חלוטו ותעלה לו ימי ספרו, V'lo sa'aleh lo yimei chaluto v'sa'aleh lo
yimei sipro, but how about
here? Here you're done and here you're done. So let the shaving
of a נזיר טהור nazir tahor count for the end of the
מצורע, metzora, like let this double count if you're in these two
stages, okay, because here you're done and here you're done, okay. וזהו
אמר להן V'zehu amar lahen and he said to that, no. אילו
זה לפני זריקת דמים וזה לפני זריקת דמים יפה אתם אומרים. Ilu
zeh lifnei zrikas damim v'zeh lifnei zrikas damim yafeh atem omrim. If
they both came before the קרבן korban they'd be similar. אלא מצורע
לפני זריקת דמים Ella metzora lifnei zrikas damim because that's on day
seven and this is day eight. ונזיר לאחר זריקת דמים V'nazir l'achar
zrikas damim and this comes after the קרבנות. korbanos. So clearly they're
doing something different and they can't double count. Wait what does that
matter? No no but if you happen to be both at the
same time. I mean the time period. You mean this is seven
days and this is 30 days. Yeah okay but when they're actually
functioning that was to get you to that point but here he's
actually saying in the way they're functioning ritually this is the beginning
of a process, this is the end. This somehow is a lead
in to a קרבן korban and this comes after a קרבן korban
so they're functioning in different ways. Okay. So ולא תעלה לו ימי
צרעתו ונזירותו ותעלה לו ימי צרעתו וטומאתו. V'lo sa'aleh lo yimei tzarato
u'neziruto v'sa'aleh lo yimei tzarato v'tumato. One minute. How about having it
count for a נזיר טמא nazir tamei which comes before the קרבן
korban and a end of the מצורע metzora that comes before the
קרבן? korban? Okay. So you could have I guess said that this
is לגדל legadel but right because you could have pointed out that
that's the beginning of a process
not the end. But here anyway both of them come before the
קרבן. korban. So let's see what the answer is. אמר להן אילו
זה לפני ביאת מים וזה לפני ביאת מים יפה אתם אומרים. Amar
lahen ilu zeh lifnei bias mayim v'zeh lifnei bias mayim yafeh atem
omrim. If they both came before going to the מקוה mikvah fine.
אלא טמא לאחר ביאת מים. Ella tamei l'achar bias mayim. Here the
גילוח giluach is this is the process of טהרה taharah and then
sprinkling the אפר פרה אדומה efer parah adumah going to the מקוה
mikvah and after the process of טהרה taharah it comes after the
טהרה taharah process, ומצורע לפני ביאת מים u'metzora lifnei bias mayim and
this comes before, so this is part of the טהרה taharah process,
it comes before the מקוה mikvah and this comes at the end
of the טהרה taharah process so it's doing something again functionally different.
So how does it actually matter? Alright that was his understanding. From
here anyway you see that the assumption is they don't double count.
Okay. But right did it develop based on this logic was it
a מסורה masorah and then was explained? But he basically says like
if you wanted to I would say the burden of proof
is on the other side.
If you wanted to double count you have to show that it's
doing the same thing. And in each one of these there's something
different about every single one from the other. Right. Structure is very
close. Right exactly. Okay. ותעלה לו V'sa'aleh lo now... did we finish
that one minute... שלא תעלה לו ימי ספרו ונזירותו ותעלה לו ימי
חלוטו וטומאתו... She'lo sa'aleh lo yimei sipro u'neziruto v'sa'aleh lo yimei chaluto
v'tumato... דזה לגדל וזה לגדל. D'zeh legadel v'zeh legadel. That's a question.
I'm sorry. Oh ותעלה לו ימי חלוטו V'sa'aleh lo yimei chaluto wait
a minute... אמר לו... Amar lo... לפני ביאת מים. lifnei bias mayim.
אמר לו יפה אמרת שלא תעלה לו ימי ספרו ולנזירותו. Amar lo
yafeh amarta she'lo sa'aleh lo yimei sipro u'lineziruto. So this one down
here right doesn't count doesn't count לימי נזירותו ולימי ספרו. l'yimei neziruto
u'l'yimei sipro. ספרו Sipro is the second stage. ותעלה לו ימי חלוטו
וטומאתו. V'sa'aleh lo yimei chaluto v'tumato. Now this is exactly what we
have why doesn't this and this count? The first one. Right. Okay
now again it's a funny question because this comes before the מקוה.
mikvah. This comes after. So this is really like almost like now
now we're really like sort of doing like a לישנא אחרינא. lishna
achrina. We're sort of saying it again. דזה לגדל וזה לגדל. D'zeh
legadel v'zeh legadel. זה לגדל וזה לגדל, zeh legadel vezeh legadel, each
one here is the the beginning of a second pro leading into
a second גילוח. giluach. הוא אומר להן, hu omer lahen, נזיר טהור
Nazir Tahor and וזה לגדל הוא? vezeh legadel hu? אמר להן, amar
lahen, he said to them, נזיר טהור והוא מצורע, Nazir Tahor vehu
metzora, זה לגדל וזה להעביר. zeh legadel vezeh leha'avir. Like it's funny,
like it didn't really have the answer. There's sort of like some
different variation of the same discussion going on. So he said to
them נזיר טהור והוא מצורע, Nazir Tahor vehu metzora, זה לגדל וזה
להעביר. zeh legadel vezeh leha'avir. Here it's להעביר leha'avir and this is
לגדל. legadel. That's going back to that. ואם נזיר טמא והוא מצורע,
ve'im Nazir tamei vehu metzora, and if this and this, which is
the question that they asked, זה לפני ביאת מים, zeh lifnei bi'at
mayim, this is before, וזה לאחר ביאת מים, vezeh le'achar bi'at mayim,
and this is afterwards. Okay. So basically the same point. Whatever ones
you compare, it's they're either different, there are differences. תני רבי חייא.
tani Rabbi Chiya. Okay, let's just finish this. תני רבי חייא, tani
Rabbi Chiya, רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya taught, זה לפני ביאת מים וזה
לאחר ביאת מים, zeh lifnei bi'at mayim vezeh le'achar bi'at mayim, זה
לפני זריקת דמים וזה לאחר זריקת דמים. zeh lifnei zrikat damim vezeh
le'achar zrikat damim. A short way of distilling what the differences are.
Pay attention. Does it come before or after the מקוה? mikvah? Does
it come before or after the קרבן? korban? Is it the first
stage or the second stage? Once you look at those three issues,
you'll see that none of them match up. Okay. Should we try
to just finish the פרק? perek? Okay, we'll just give it two
minutes because we really have to clear out. There's a class starting
here in four minutes. Okay, תגלחת הנגע. tigulchat hanega. So you know
what? Let's not. Okay, I know it's very tempting, but let's stop
here. All right, very good. רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, רבי שמעון בן
יוחאי. Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai. Correct, because there's a long note.